Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף daf is שבועות מ"ו Shavuos
Mem-Vav and as we record this our hearts and prayers are with
אחינו בני ישראל Acheinu Bnei Yisrael in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael מדינת
ישראל Medinat Yisrael for the safety and security of everyone during these
difficult times. Okay we pick up at the bottom of מ"ה עמוד
ב' Mem-He Amud Bet and we are on אמר רמי בר חמא
Amar Rami Bar Chama the end of the first wide line and
we had just had a whole discussion
that the משנה Mishna where we're dealing with a שבועה shvua of
the שכיר sachir of the hired hand that he can make the
שבועה shvua that he did not get paid and collect from the
בעל הבית baal habayit was only when he was hired with witnesses.
But if there's no evidence to the fact that he was hired
then he does not make the שבועה shvua because the בעל הבית
baal habayit could have just said I never even hired you so
he's believed to say I hired you and I paid your wage.
So אמר רמי בר חמא Amar Rami Bar Chama first end of
the first wide line on מ"ה עמוד ב' Mem-He Amud Bet says
Rami Bar Chama כמה מעליא האי שמעתתא Kama Ma'alya Hai Shma'atata how
wonderful is this teaching? It makes so much sense this qualification of
the משנה. Mishna. אמר ליה רבא Amlei Rava so Rava said back
to him מאי מעליותא Mai Maylusa what makes you think it's so
great? There's actually a lot of logical problems with it. Maybe I
understand the סברא svara but if you assume that that's true then
there's a lot of questions to be asked. אם כן שבועת שומרים
דחייב רחמנא היכי משכחת לה? Im ken shvuat shomrim dechayev rachmana heichi
mishkachat la? The very case in the תורה Torah where somebody makes
an oath and says that something happened it was it got damaged
without פשיעה pshia it wasn't negligent there was an אונס ones it
was a גניבה ואבידה gneiva va-aveida whatever the שומר shomer is making
an oath to and he's believed. Why do you even need to
make the oath? היכי משכחת לה? Heichi mishkachat la? מתוך שיכול לומר
לא היו דברים מעולם יכול לומר לא נאנסו. Mitoch sheyachol lomar lo
hayu devarim me'olam yachol lomar lo ne'ensu. So he could have just
said I never agreed to watch the object you're making this whole
thing up לא היו דברים מעולם. lo hayu devarim me'olam. So you
should believe me when I say that some accident happened to it
that was beyond my control you should believe me without a שבועה
shvua because I could have just have denied that I ever even
took it under my possession. So the obvious answer
is דאפקדיה בעדים. de'afkedei be'edim. So you'll say fine like we're sort
of saying by our משנה. Mishna. Maybe all the cases in the
תורה Torah where you have to make a שבועת שומרים shvuat shomrim
is when there's evidence to the fact that you gave over that
object for safekeeping there were witnesses. דאפקדיה בעדים. de'afkedei be'edim. מתוך שיכול
לומר החזרתי לך יכול לומר לא נאנסו. Mitoch sheyachol lomar hachzarti lach
yachol lomar lo ne'ensu. All right so but then I got another
problem once you're applying this מיגו migo here and מיגו migo as
a way of getting out of a שבועה shvua then even in
a case when there are witnesses that the object was entrusted he
could say that I gave it back right? Somebody is believed unless
there's a שטר shtar you're believed to say whether it's borrowed money
or whether it's a פקדון pikadon whether it's something that's given over
to you to be watched even if there's witnesses that you received
it you're believed to say that you returned it. So again you
see since that doesn't work that we don't say this type of
a מיגו migo to exempt somebody from a שבועה. shvua. So the
גמרא Gemara says no דאפקדיה בשטרא. de'afkedei bishtara. Well you could say
all the cases in the תורה Torah of שבועת שומרים shvuat shomrim
is if the פקדון pikadon was given over with a שטר. shtar.
And the שטר shtar basically either I the person who am entrusting
the object to you has a document that you've signed that says
that you're watching my object and then when I come and had
what happened to it you can't say you never received it I
have the evidence I have the document. You can't say you gave
it back to
me because then שטרך ביד בעל הבית מאי בעי? shtarcha beyad baal
habayit mai ba'ei? Why am I still holding on to the שטר?
shtar? So that's the only case in the תורה Torah according to
this it would be a שבועת שומרים shvuat shomrim was if the
פקדון pikadon was given over with a
שטר. shtar. מכלל michlal says the גמרא Gemara from that we can
infer so מכלל דתרוייהו סבירא להו המפקיד אצל חברו בעדים אין צריך
להחזירו לו בעדים בשטרא צריך להחזירו
לו בעדים. michlal de-travaihu savira lehu hamakid etzel chaveiro be'edim ein tzarich
lehachazir lo be'edim bishtara tzarich lehachazir lo be'edim. So from this the
back and forth here we can infer that everybody basically agrees to
the principles of this back and forth. And the principles that you're
saying basically is that if you entrust something to somebody with witnesses
you do not need witnesses on the return. You're basically believed to
say I returned it even without witnesses and that's
why in order to answer the question about what about the מיגו
migo you had to say we're talking about a case of שטר.
shtar. So it seems that both of you agree you are believed
to say you returned it even though even without bringing evidence to
that. However if there was a שטר shtar you're not believed then
you would need witnesses or you would need to be holding on
to the שטר shtar because then the fact that the other person
is holding on to the שטר shtar serves as prima facie evidence
that you did not return it. All right. קרי רמי בר חמא
ליה לרב ששת וישם דוד את הדברים
האלה בלבבו.
Kari Rami Bar Chama lei-Rav Sheshet vayyassem David et hadevarim
ha'eleh bilvavo. So this פסוק pasuk that דוד David sort of put
this matter to his heart he said that that is what Rami
Bar Chama said like רב ששת Rav Sheshet put this matter to
his heart to try to understand like is this idea that we're
talking in our משנה Mishna and then also Analogously by שבועת השומרים
shevuat hashomrim only that there were witnesses that the object was handed
over while in the משנה mishna that he was hired בעדים be'edim
and by the שבועת השומרים shevuat hashomrim that there were witnesses that
the object was entrusted בעדים. be'edim. So he really wanted to put
this matter to his heart to see whether this is how we
actually hold or not. Where do we see this?
דאשכחיה רב ששת לרבה בר שמואל. De'ashkechei Rav Sheshet leRabbah bar Shmuel.
Because רב ששת Rav Sheshet found רבה בר שמואל. Rabbah bar Shmuel.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, תני מר מידי בשכיר? Tani Mar midi besachir?
Have you taught anything relating to the case of the שכיר sachir
in the משנה? mishna? So אמר ליה, Amar lei, אין, In, yes,
תנינא, Tanina, we taught, שכיר בזמנו נשבע ונוטל. Sachir bizmano nishba venotel.
כיצד? Keitzad?
So the שכיר sachir can make a שבועה, shvua, while it's still
the time in which he would be collecting, he can make a
שבועה shvua and collect his money that he has not received it
yet. He can make that שבועה. shvua. כיצד? Keitzad? How is this
true? בזמן שאמר לו שכרתני ולא נתת לי שכרי והלה אומר שכרתיך
ונתתי לך שכרך. Bizman she'amar lo sechartani velo natata li schari vehala
omer secharticha venatati lecha scharecha. What is the context says in this
ברייתא braita that you can make the שבועה shvua when they're debating
whether he has been paid or not? Okay, he says you hired
me and you didn't pay, and he says I hired you and
I did pay. אבל אמר לו שתים קצצת לי והלה אומר לא
קצצתי לך אלא אחת. Aval amar lo shtayim katzatzta li vehala omer
lo katzatzti lecha ela achat.
But let's say they both agree he hasn't been paid yet, but
they're debating what were the wages. The
שכיר sachir says you committed to me twenty dollars for the day's
work, and he said no, only ten dollars. Okay. המוציא מחבירו עליו
הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya.
So that's a classic case of a מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzat. That's
not the שבועת שכיר. shvuat sachir. I say you owe me twenty,
you say only ten, and המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav
hara'aya.
So we'll see, I mean, the ראיה raya here means that basically
now we'll see that this ראיה, raya, I mean this ראיה raya
here means that if the שכיר sachir wants to get the extra
ten dollars that they're being debated,
he needs to bring evidence. Presumably the בעל הבית ba'al habayit would
have to be נשבע. nishba. It's a case of like מודה במקצת
modeh bemiktzat and the בעל הבית ba'al habayit would have to be
נשבע nishba that he did not,
that he only agreed to ten dollars, not to twenty dollars. Okay
fine, but at the end of the day the שכיר sachir does
not have it in his power to collect the extra ten dollars
that they're debating unless he brings witnesses. He cannot take a שבועה
shvua like he can in the normal case of the שבועת שכיר.
shvuat sachir. Okay, so you could have imagined this משנה mishna saying
that if it's two, he says two and he says one, the
בעל הבית ba'al habayit is נשבע מודה במקצת, nishba modeh bemiktzat, but
it's focusing here, which is true, and we'll see that in a
minute in the גמרא, Gemara, but it's focusing here on the שכיר.
sachir. And it's saying in a classic case a שכיר sachir could
be נשבע. nishba. In this case, maybe it's true the בעל הבית
ba'al habayit has to be נשבע, nishba, but the שכיר sachir can't
do anything, he doesn't have the power to do anything on his
own unless he brings proof that it was twenty dollars, not ten
dollars. Okay, so now how is this relevant to the question about
whether you need witnesses whether you were hired or not? So let's
take a look. המדי סיפא בראיה הוי רישא בלא ראיה. Hami deseiifa
biraya havi reisha belo raya. So he inferred like this: since the
סיפא seifa spoke about bringing witnesses, the שכיר sachir has to bring
witnesses when they're debating ten dollars or twenty dollars, it implies that
at the רישא reisha where the שכיר sachir makes his classic שבועה
shvua and collects, he does it without any witnesses. So you see
you do not need witnesses that you were hired. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so that's his proof against רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, says רב נחמן
בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, top of מו עמוד א. mem
vav amud aleph. רישא וסיפא בראיה. Reisha veseifa biraya. No, not necessarily.
Even in the first case where the שכיר sachir makes his classic
שבועת שכיר shvuat sachir and collects where they're debating whether he was
paid or not, it could be he has to bring witnesses that
he was hired. And the end you're bringing witnesses that it was
twenty dollars, not ten dollars. So why did it only mention ראיה
raya at the end, the עדים edim at the end? ראיה דלשלם
קתני ראיה דשבועה לא קתני. Raya dileshalem katani raya deshvu'ah lo katani.
It's talking about when your witnesses are needed to win the day.
So in the second case, I mean when the witnesses are going
to be the circumstances under which you're going to get paid. So
in the second case where they're debating ten or twenty, the שכיר
sachir can't without witnesses, he needs witnesses if he wants to get
paid. So that's why it says המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero
alav hara'aya. In the first case, yes, he needs witnesses if he
wants to make a שבועה, shvua, but the witnesses are not to
get him to get paid, the witnesses are to create the context
in which he makes the שבועה. shvua. Okay? So he says it
is perfectly possible that in the first case there were witnesses that
set the groundwork for the שבועה, shvua, but we're only going to
use the phrase המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya when
we're talking about that the only way you can get paid is
with witnesses testifying to the debt itself. Okay. So you can't prove
one way or the other from that whether you need witnesses that
you were hired. אמר רב ירמיה בר אבא, Amar Rav Yirmiyah bar
Abba, שלחו ליה מבי רב לשמואל. Shalchu lei mibei Rav leShmuel. They
sent from the ישיבה yeshiva of רב Rav to שמואל. Shmuel. ילמדנו
רבינו, Yelamdenu Rabbeinu, let our master teach us. אומן אומר שתים קצצת
לי. Uman omer shtayim katzatzta li. Exactly this case in the ברייתא.
braita. You know, the worker says you agreed to two, I've been
saying twenty dollars, make it more substantial, let's call it, I don't
know, two hundred dollars. והלה אומר לא קצצתי לך אלא אחת. Vehala
omer lo katzatzti lecha ela achat. No, I only promised you a
hundred dollars. So exactly this, they're not debating whether he was paid,
they're debating what's owed,
you know, what the amount was that they agreed on. מי נשבע?
mi nishba? Can he take a שבועה? shvuah? So this is asking
the question without the context of the ברייתא baraita that already directly
answered it. And the logic might be that since we're saying that
the purpose of the שבועת שכיר shvuas sachir is because the בעל
הבית ba'al habayis isn't paying attention who he paid or not, so
maybe he's also not paying attention how much they agreed in terms
of the wages and maybe here also they allow the שכיר sachir
to make a שבועה. shvuah. So אמר להן, amar lahen, so שמואל
Shmuel sent back to רב's Rav ישיבה, yeshiva, בזו ישבע בעל הבית
ויפסיד אומן. bezo yishava ba'al habayis v'yafsid uman. Here the בעל הבית
ba'al habayis takes the שבועה, shvuah, מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, that's what
we were saying in the ברייתא, baraita, and sorry, the אומן uman
is loses out unless he can bring real witnesses. Why? קציצה ודאי
מדכר דכיר אינשי. katzitza vadai midkar dachir inshi. People definitely remember how
much they agreed to, the wages that they said, that they remember.
There's so many different workers I have to pay, it could be
that I forgot I paid a particular one, but what are the
wages I'm going by, that I remember. Also when we're setting the
wages it's not when everybody is coming to me to get paid,
so there's also generally just more ישוב הדעת. yishuv hadaas. Okay.
איני? ini? Is this really true? והתני רבה בר שמואל? ve'ha'tanei Rabba
bar Shmuel? Didn't רבה בר שמואל Rabba bar Shmuel teach קצץ המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה? katzatz hamotzi mechavero alav haraya?
So he says, but yeah one minute, the ברייתא baraita that we
taught before said that in the case of קציצה, katzitza, right, this
is exactly what we caught,
what we quoted before, it says המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero
alav haraya. It sounds like
that the שכיר sachir has to bring witnesses and without witnesses the
בעל הבית ba'al habayis doesn't have to do anything, he doesn't even
have to be
נשבע. nishba. Okay. ואילו לא מייתי ראיה פטור. v'ilu lo maysi raya
pattur. So and the implication of that is that if he does
not bring a proof, then he's like
the בעל הבית ba'al habayis gets off scot-free if the שכיר sachir
can't bring a proof. אמאי ישבע בעל הבית ויפסיד אומן? amay yishava
ba'al habayis v'yafsid uman? So according to you, how do you fit
that with your claim that the בעל הבית ba'al habayis has to
take the שבועה? shvuah? Now it's logical the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
has to take a שבועה, shvuah, it's מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, I
was sort of reading that into the ברייתא baraita before because I
knew this גמרא Gemara coming up, but what's being said is the
simple sense of that ברייתא baraita is in that case actually we
just believe the בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, no שבועה, shvuah, and the
אומן uman has no
recourse unless he can offer being direct witnesses. So,
so now אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav
Nachman responds and this is what I had already read into the
earlier ברייתא, baraita, לצדדין קתני. litzdadin katanei. It's not saying either המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav haraya or zero although that's usually
what המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav haraya means. If the
guy can't bring a proof you get off scot-free. That's not how
to read it. או מייתי ראיה ויטול o maysi raya v'yitol
or it means now the אומן, uman, he can't take a שבועה,
shvuah, he has to bring witnesses. If he doesn't bring witnesses, או
ישבע בעל הבית ויפסיד. o yishava ba'al habayis v'yafsid. Then okay, if
the אומן uman wants to win he has to bring witnesses, but
if that's not happening, then we're not done, it's not just המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav haraya, the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
still has to make a שבועה. shvuah. Okay, so that makes sense
logically because it's a מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, it's just a little
bit of a force in the ברייתא. baraita.
Okay.
ויפסיד אומן. v'yafsid uman. Okay. מתיבי. masvei. I'll ask you on this.
הנותן טליתו לאומן. ha'noten talliso l'uman. So we got we have here
another ברייתא. baraita. Somebody gives his טלית tallis to the אומן. uman.
אומן אומר קצצת לי שתים. uman omer katzatzta li shtayim. והלה אומר
לא קצצתי לך אלא אחת. ve'halo omer lo katzatzti lecha ela achas.
ממש mamash exactly our case. Okay so exactly what we've been talking
about. So what does it say? Let's read that. הנותן טליתו לאומן
אומן אומר קצצת לי שתים והלה אומר לא קצצתי לך אלא אחת.
ha'noten talliso l'uman uman omer
katzatzta li shtayim ve'halo omer lo katzatzti lecha ela achas. Debating whether
it was two or one. כל זמן שטלית ביד אומן על בעל
הבית
להביא ראיה. kol zman she'tallis b'yad uman al haba'al habayis l'havi raya.
As long as the אומן uman let's say he's your tailor and
he's made some adjustments and you're debating how much you agreed to.
So right now the בעל הבית ba'al habayis is the המוציא מחברו.
hamotzi mechavero. The tailor is holding onto your garment and you want
me to give you your garment back, pay me what you owe
me.
So the בעל הבית ba'al habayis has to bring proof. So this
is even better than the case of the מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas,
right? In the case we were dealing with the worker didn't have
wasn't holding onto anything of the בעל הבית ba'al habayis and he
was just claiming you owe me two and the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis says I owe you one. So the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
can be נשבע nishba and get off. But here the אומן uman
is saying he's the one that's מוחזק. muchzak. He says he's holding
onto the טלית. tallis. He's saying if you want your טלית tallis
back, you gotta give I'm claiming you owe me two. You have
to prove less if you want me to give you your טלית
tallis for less. Okay so in that case he can if the
בעל הבית ba'al habayis can't bring a proof then the אומן uman
can get the full two that he's claiming he's owed.
על בעל הבית להביא ראיה. al haba'al habayis l'havi raya. נתנה לו
בזמנו. nasna lo bizmano. However if
the אומן uman gave back the טלית tallis during the time that
that they had sort of agreed that the work was getting done.
נשבע ונוטל. nishba v'notel. עבר זמנו המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. avar zmano
hamotzi mechavero alav haraya. So if it was during the time that
the אומן uman would collect then it's שבועת ה, shvuas ha, then
it's like the שבועת שכיר. shvuas sachir. So he can make a
שבועה shvuah that he hasn't been paid the full amount even though
they're debating how much, not whether he's been paid or not. According
this sounds like the שבועה shvuah of the שכיר sachir applies even...
even in a case of debating the amount. So, during, when it's
בזמנו *bizmano*, he can be נשבע *nishba* and collect. עבר זמנו המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה *Avar zmano hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya*, but once it's
after the normal time that payments are being made, then there's no
more the שבועה shevuah *shvua* of the שכיר sachir *sochir* and you
go back to המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה *hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya*. So,
the first part was interesting. We weren't dealing with a case like
that because we didn't have the אומן *uman* being מחזיק *machzik* in
something. The last case of עבר זמנו המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה *Avar
zmano hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya* is a little strange, you know, that
gets back to our question of whether that's a מודה במקצת modeh
bemiktzas, *modeh bamikzas* when the אומן *uman* says two and the בעל
הבית baal habayis *ba'al habayis* says one. But what's most interesting for
us is the middle case, because the middle case sounds like that
during the period of when, you know, payments are being made, זמנו
*zmano*, there still is a שבועת שכיר shvuas sachir *shvuas sochir*, which
and we were saying there isn't a שבועת שכיר shvuas sachir *shvuas
sochir* in the case of where they're debating קצץ katzatz, *katzatz*, where
they're debating what the rate was. So let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. בזמנו מי אישבע ונוטל *Bizmano mi
ishva venotel?* So you see that during the time the שכיר sachir
*sochir* is empowered to be נשבע ונוטל nishba venotel, *nishba venotel*, the
שבועת שכיר sachir. *shvuas sochir* applies? אמאי *Amai?* Why is this true?
According to what you said, ישבע בעל הבית baal habayis ויפסיד אומן
*yishava ba'al habayis veyafsiad uman*. During that time when it's about how
much was the rate, there is no שבועת שכיר sachir *shvuas sochir*
and the בעל הבית baal habayis *ba'al habayis* could take a שבועה
shvuah *shvua* of מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas, *modeh bamikzas* and the אומן
*uman* would lose. אמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman בר יצחק הא מני
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda היא דאמר כל זמן שהשבועה נותה אצל בעל
הבית baal habayis שכיר sachir. נשבע ונוטל *Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak,
Ha meni Rabbi Yehuda hi, de'amar kol zman shehashvua nota etzel ba'al
habayis sochir nishba venotel*. You know what, you're right. Okay, that ברייתא
beraita *braisa* does assume that שבועת שכיר sachir, *shvuas sochir* applies even
in a case of קצץ katzatz? *katzatz*. But that's only the position
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. It's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* who holds that that whenever there would, you know, normally
you would think that the בעל הבית baal habayis *ba'al habayis* would
make a שבועה shvuah *shvua*, חז״ל *Chazal* were מתקן *metaken* that the
שכיר sachir. *sochir* makes a שבועה Shvua *shvua*. So logically of course
that should be a מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas, *modeh bamikzas*, but nevertheless,
since it's בזמנו *bizmano*, the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* basically
holds whenever it's בזמנו *bizmano*, they let the שכיר sachir *sochir* make
a שבועה Shvua *shvua*, even in a case of קצץ katzatz *katzatz*.
Okay? So that's a, okay, claim that there's a debate of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* and the חכמים *Chachamim*. Let's forget which
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* you're talking about. היי רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda *Hai Rabbi Yehuda?* Which רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
are you saying makes this claim that the שכיר sachir *sochir* can
always make it, even in a case of קצץ katzatz, *katzatz*? אילימא
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda דמתניתין *Eilima Rabbi Yehuda demasnisein*, if you're going
to say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* of our משנה Mishnah
*mishna*, הא אחמורי קא מחמיר machmir, *ha achmuri kamachmir*. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* of our משנה Mishnah *mishna* is stricter on the
שכיר *sochir*, gives the שכיר *sochir* less of an ability to make
a שבועה Shvua, *shvua*. Why? דתנן רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר עד
שתהא שם מקצת הודאה *Detnan, Rabbi Yehuda omer, ad shetei sham mikzas
hoda'ah*, that he does not allow for the idea of a שבועת
שכיר *shvuas sochir* until there's a case of a מודה במקצת modeh
bemiktzas? *modeh bamikzas*. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is narrowing
the scope of שבועת שכיר *shvuas sochir*. Why are you saying that
he is broadening it to include cases where they're debating קצץ katzatz
*katzatz*?
So,
where were we? אלא רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda דברייתא *Ela Rabbi Yehuda
de'braisa*. Fine, it's רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* of the ברייתא beraita *braisa*.
דתניא שכיר כל זמן שלא עבר עליו זמנו הרי זה נשבע ונוטל
ואם לאו אינו נשבע ונוטל *Detanya, sochir kol zman shelo avar alav
zmano harei zeh nishba venotel ve'im lav eino nishba venotel*. Okay, so
that's the ברייתא beraita *braisa* that says that the שכיר *sochir* can
only make the שבועה Shvua *shvua* during the period in which it's
considered זמנו *zmano* to be collecting. ואמר רבי יהודה *Ve'amar Rabbi Yehuda*,
and in that ברייתא beraita *braisa*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says, אימתי
*eimasai?*
When is that true? בזמן שאמר לו תן לי שכרי חמשים דינר
שיש לי בידך והוא אומר התקבלת מהן דינר זהב *Bizman she'amar lo
ten li schari chamishim dinar sheyesh li beyadcha vehu omer hitkabalta meihen
dinar zahav*. Okay, so now it's רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* articulating his
מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas, *modeh bamikzas* position. If he's saying give me
50 and the בעל הבית baal habayis *ba'al habayis* is saying I
already gave you 25. Okay? That's when there's a מודה במקצת modeh
bemiktzas *modeh bamikzas*, then we let the שכיר *sochir* make the שבועה
Shvua? *shvua*. או שאמר לו שתים קצצת לי והלה אומר לא קצצתי
לך אלא אחת *O she'amar lo shtayim katzatzta li vehala omer lo
katzatzti lecha ela achas*. So you see, this is exactly— so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was not just making an אוקימתא *okimta*. Here it's
explicit in the ברייתא *braisa* that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is saying
that they make a שבועת שכיר *shvuas sochir* either if they're debating
how much he got paid or if they're debating what the rate
was that was set. Exactly in the case of קצצת לי *katzatzta
li*, it's explicit in the ברייתא *braisa* that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
is saying that there is a שבועת שכיר *shvuas sochir*. אבל אמר
לו לא שכרתיך מעולם *Aval amar lo lo scharticha mei'olam*, but if
he's saying I never hired you, או שאמר לו שכרתיך ונתתי לך
שכרך *o she'amar lo scharticha venasasi lecha scharcha*, or he says I
hired you but I paid you in full, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה
*hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya*. So then it's המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה *hamotzi
mechavero alav hara'aya*. So what do you see? You see that רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says two things. On the one hand, רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* says they only made a שבועת שכיר *shvuas sochir* when
it's מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas, *modeh bamikzas*. But on the other hand,
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says they made a שבועת שכיר *shvuas sochir*
even in a case of קצצת לי *katzatzta li*. You know, even
though the חכמים *Chachamim* would say that in that case, you know,
the בעל הבית baal habayis *ba'al habayis* is נשבע *nishba* and it
would not, you know, and and they weren't מתקן שבועת שכיר *metaken
shvuas sochir* by— when they're debating how much was the rate, רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says there is a שבועת שכיר *shvuas sochir*. So
narrower only in a case when it's מודה במקצת Modeh Bemiktzas. *modeh
bamikzas*, broader that it includes even a case when they're debating what
the rate was. And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to understand
what the logic is behind this, although you might already have figured
it out.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, מתקיף לה רב ששת
בריה דרב אידי *Maskif lah Rav Sheshes brei de'Rav Idi*, so Rav
Sheshes bar Rav Idi challenges. אלא קצץ katzatz רבי יהודה היא ולא
רבנן? Rabbanan. Wait a minute, you're telling me that the case of
when they're debating what the rate was, רבי יהודה says they made
the שבועה Shvua. and not the Rabbis?
השתא, Hashta, how does this make sense? היכי דמחמיר Heichi demachmir רבי
יהודה מקילי mikili רבנן. Rabbanan? Where רבי יהודה is strict, says you
need a מודה במקצת, the Rabbis are lenient. They say you don't
need a מודה במקצת, even if they're debating, you know, he says
I didn't pay you anything, and he
says—the שכיר says you didn't pay me anything, and the בעל הבית
baal habayis says I paid you in full. So, and רבי יהודה
needs a מודה במקצת, so in that case רבי יהודה limits the
שבועת השכיר, shvuas hasachir, and the Rabbis are broader. היכא דמיקל Heicha
demeka רבי יהודה, when רבי יהודה is lenient, meaning he broadens the
שבועת השכיר shvuas hasachir and allows it in a case of קצץ,
katzatz. מחמיר רבנן? machmir Rabbanan? So the Rabbis are going to be
strict and say that you—we didn't allow it in a case of
מודה במקצת? How does that make sense? I mean, excuse me, we
didn't allow it in a case of קצץ? katzatz. How does it
make sense that they're reversing each other, who's the מחמיר, machmir, who's
the מיקל? meikel? And the answer is obviously going to be, it's
not all about חומרא chumra and קולא, kula, there's a logic here,
but we'll get to that. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ואלא מאי, Ve'ela mai, רבנן? Rabbanan. So what do you want to
say? You want to say that קצץ katzatz. is the Rabbis, and
that every—and that you know, according to the Rabbis, even the Rabbis
who generally broaden and say you don't need מודה במקצת, they also
say that you can make a שבועת שכיר in a case where
they're debating the rate? ואלא הא דתני רבה בר שמואל: קצץ, המוציא
מחבירו עליו הראיה. מאן? Ve'ela hadetani Rabba bar Shmuel: Katzatz, hamotzi mechavero
alav hara'aya. Man? לא רבי יהודה ולא רבנן. Lo Rabbi Yehuda velo
Rabbanan. You can't say that. You can't say like, oh everybody agrees
for קצץ, katzatz. even the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Because we have
two ברייתות beraisos that are conflicting. We have the ברייתא we quoted
at the bottom of the עמוד ב amud beis that said with
קצץ they did not make the תקנת שכיר, takanas sachir, המוציא מחבירו
עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya,
and here we have a ברייתא where רבי יהודה explicitly says with
קצץ they did make the תקנת שכיר. takanas sachir. So clearly you
cannot say that everybody agrees to קצץ. And we know that רבי
יהודה says they made it, and we have another ברייתא that says
they didn't make it, so clearly it is a debate of רבי
יהודה and the רבנן. Rabbanan רבי יהודה says they did make the
תקנה, takana, and the ברייתא is the רבנן that says they did
not. Okay, so now we got the problem, who's the מחמיר, machmir
who's the מיקל? meikel? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא
אמר רבא: בהא קמיפלגי. Ela amar Rava: Beha kamifligi.
Here's the debate. It has nothing to do with חומרא chumra and
קולא. kula. It has to do with how are we conceptualizing what
this שבועת שכיר is. רבי יהודה סבר: בדאורייתא עבדו ליה תקנתא לשכיר,
ובדרבנן הוי תקנתא, ותקנתא לתקנתא לא עבדינן. Rabbi Yehuda savar: Bedioraisa avdu
lei takanta l'sachir, ub'drabbanan havei takanta, vetakanta l'takanta lo avdinan. רבי יהודה
says:
We're not discussing does the בעל הבית Ba'al Habayis remember, does he
not remember, you know, that's the mindset of the Rabbis, and that's
why they say it doesn't apply to when they're debating the rate
because he definitely would remember the rate. רבי יהודה says that is
not my way of conceptualizing this at all. The way I conceptualize
this is what חז"ל Chazal did is they said: Whenever you have
a debate between the שכיר and the בעל הבית ba'al ha'bayit about
whether he's been paid or what the rate was, if you can
start with a שבועה דאורייתא shvuah dioraisa in a case in which
the בעל הבית ba'al ha'bayit would be a מודה במקצת and make
a שבועה דאורייתא shvuah dioraisa and be פטור, patur, they reversed it
and they put it on the שכיר. That's the language the גמרא
Gemara used earlier: כל היכא דשבועה נחיתא אצל בעל הבית, kol heicha
deshvuah nechisa etzel baal habayis, שדיוה אשכיר. shdu ah sachir. So it's
not based on a particular: "Oh, I probably forgot" or whatever. No,
obviously they're concerns that the בעל הבית is going to forget. But
rather than worrying case-by-case, what they did structurally is they said whenever
there's a שבועת מודה במקצת, shvuas modeh bemiktzas, the שכיר gets it
and he gets to be נוטל. notel. That's why he's limited, it's
only מודה במקצת, but it also includes even the case of קצץ.
When the בעל הבית is a כופר הכל, kofer hakol, then he
would only make a שבועה shvuah like a שבועת היסת, shvuas hesset,
ותקנתא לתקנתא לא עבדינן, vetakanta letakanta lo avdinan, there they're not going
to give it to a שכיר. So for him, he's focused more
on like form, if you would, than function. And we have to
start first with the שבועת מודה במקצת shvuas modeh bemiktzas and then
we put it on the שכיר, but then it'll apply even in
a case of קצץ. ורבנן סברי: בדרבנן נמי עבדינן תקנתא לשכיר, וקציצה
מדכר דכיר. VeRabbanan savri: Bedrabbanan nami avdinan takanta l'sachir, v'katzitzah midchar dachir.
And the Rabbis say it's not about reversing from the בעל הבית
to the שכיר. You know, they
say it'll apply even by a דרבנן drabbanan of a שבועת היסת.
shvuas hesset. But that's not what it's about. It's about a תקנה
takana that we did that the שכיר gets to make a שבועה
shvuah in cases where the בעל הבית would forget. But that would
not apply to קצץ. So there's a conceptual debate and it leads
one of them to be מחמיר in one place and to be
מיקל meikel in the other, and the other the reverse. Which is
all very nice and elegant. Okay, so now we move on to
the next part of the משנה mishnah of השבועה נשבעין ונוטלין. hashvua
nishba'in venotlin. We're done with the case of שכיר and we deal
with the case of נגזל, nignzal, somebody who was robbed. And the
case: נגזל כיצד? היו עדים שנכנס לביתו למשכנו. Nignzal, keitzad? Hayu edim
she'nichnas l'veiso l'mashkeno. So to remind you the case of the משנה
mishnah. is: Witnesses saw that somebody, ראובן, Reuven, was going into שמעון's
Shimon house with the intention of, you know, taking some objects as
collateral, but it was without permission, without permission of the owner, without
permission of the בית דין. beis din. So effectively, you know, it's
stealing. If you took them and you didn't have license, you're going
to have to return them. So in that case... the נגזל Nigzal
can say what was taken and take a שבועה shvuah and get
it back from the גזלן. Gazlan. Normally you might say המוציא מחבירו
עליו הראיה, Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya, right? If you're claiming that I
have something of yours, then you prove it to me, but here
because it was clear that he was going in to see something,
his intent was to take
something and without permission and now he's claiming he didn't take anything,
we allow the נגזל Nigzal to take a שבועה and to say
what he took and what was taken from him and to collect.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara, says. And רבי יהודה again
says you need מודה במקצת. So אפי' לא משכחו? Afilu Lo Mashkechu?
So גמרא Gemara says, okay, so what does it mean? It says
he was going into his house to take property. But maybe he
just said he was going to and he didn't do it? Why
is that enough of a basis to allow the guy, the homeowner,
שמעון Shimon to take a שבועה, just because ראובן Reuven said I'm
going to go take
something? Okay, people make exaggerated claims. That now lets שמעון Shimon make
an oath? So מי לא אמר רב נחמן? Mi Lo Amar Rav
Nachman? Doesn't רב נחמן say האי מאן דנקיט נרגא בידיה? Hai Man
Denakit Narga Beyadei? Somebody was holding on to an axe ואמר איזיל
ואקטליה לדקלא דפלניא. Ve'amar Izil Ve'aktleih Ledikla Deflanya. I'm going to go
chop down somebody's palm tree. ואשתכח דקטיל ושדי, Ve'ishtakach Dekatil Vesadi, and
you saw that the palm tree then was chopped down. לא אמרינן
דהוא קטליה. Lo Amrinan Dehu Katleih. You don't say that the guy
chopped it down even though sometimes by דיני ממונות Dinei Mamonos you
go by circumstantial evidence, this isn't enough. Why? אמר אביי אינשי גזימי
ולא עבדי. Amar Abaye Inshi Gezimi Velo Avdi. People make exaggerated claims
and they don't do it. You know, like a classic murder mystery
on TV, somebody says I'm going to kill you, not evidence that
the person actually killed the person.
So if somebody says I'm going to go in and take, take
something for that loan, that's not, people will say things. That's not
enough of a basis to give the נגזל Nigzal to give the
homeowner the right to make a שבועה and to collect. So גמרא
Gemara, says הכא
נמי דגזים ולא עביד. Hacha Nami Degazim Velo Avid. Let's say here
he's just exaggerating. אימא ומשכחו. Eima Umashkechu. Okay, no, no, so there
are witnesses that ראובן Reuven went into the house and actually took
vessels. Okay, well if there are actually witnesses that he took something,
then why do you need the שבועה? So the גמרא Gemara. says
ולחזי מאי משכח. Velichezei Mai Mashkechu. Why don't we see what he
took? So אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbah
Bar Bar Channah Amar Rabbi Yochanan בטוענו כלים הניטלים תחת כנפיו. Betono
Keilim Hanitalim Tachat Knafav. They did not see, they see he took
something but they didn't see what it was. They said we saw
you take something and put it into your under your garment or
in your bag and we didn't see what it was. And now
you let the homeowner take an oath what it was.
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, says
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
excuse me, okay, ראו שהטמין כלים תחת כנפיו ויצא. Ra'u Shehitmin Keilim
Tachat Knafav Veyatza. So let's say exactly this case, they saw somebody
hide some, take some object from the homeowner and put it under
his in his garment and he walked out. It's like a classic
case of
shoplifting in a store, somebody like
surreptitiously dropped something in their bag, puts it, puts it under their
coat. ואמר לקוחין הן בידי. Ve'amar Lekuchin Hen Beyadi. And now what
is this guy claiming? So we're assuming that the guy is like
denying he took anything or maybe saying he so that's like a
כופר הכל. Kofer Hakol. And then we let the נגזל Nigzal take
a שבועה. Let's say he actually admits that he, that he took
something, but he says I bought it. Okay, again, just like a
shoplifting case. So you find he claims that he bought it. אינו
נאמן. Eino Ne'eman.
He's not believed. All right, why not? Isn't somebody believed as something
that's in their possession to say they bought it? So let's take
a look. ואמרינן אלא בבעל הבית שאינו עשוי למכור כליו. Ve'amrinan Ela
Beba'al Habayis She'eino Asuy Limkor Keilav. That's only true if you're dealing
with a homeowner that normally doesn't sell an object. You know, again,
in the case of the shoplifting, you would say show me your
receipt. But if you're not dealing in a context of receipts, if
I go into somebody's house and then I walk out with their
nice vase, I can say, can I say I bought it from
him or am I assumed to have stolen it from him if
that's what he claims? Normally we say חזקה מה שתחת יד אדם
הרי הוא שלו. Chazaka Ma SheTachat Yad Adam Harei Hu Shelo. It's
all very nice, we knew the בעל הבית owned it, but that's
the point of the חזקה, Chazaka, that people buy and sell things.
So now I'm in possession of it, I should be believed to
say that I bought it. But here it's saying you're not. Why
not? So it's making it clear by adding these criteria that we're
talking about a case that it's a homeowner does not normally sell
the objects in his home. I don't normally sell my vases to
people that come and visit me. If I have a store, obviously
somebody's believed to say they purchased something they walk out of the
store. Okay, so that makes sense, that's an interesting new הלכה Halacha
about the חזקה מה שתחת יד אדם, Chazaka Ma SheTachat Yad Adam,
that in this type of a case where we know you got
it from going into the house and homeowners normally don't sell
their personal items, you're not believed.
אבל בבעל הבית העשוי למכור כליו, Aval Beba'al Habayis Ha'asuy Limkor Keilav,
but if you're dealing with a homeowner that sometimes does sell his
objects from the home. נאמן, ne'eman, you would be believed ושאין עשוי
למכור כלים נמי לא אמרן אלא בדברים שאין דרכן להטמין. Ushe'ein asuy
limkor kelim nami lo amran ela bidvarim she'ein darkan lehatmin. And even
when it is a homeowner that normally doesn't sell his vessels, so
in a case where you're not believed, that's only in a case
also that there's things that are not normally hidden. So then the
question is, so why are you hiding it? So it's the combination
of factors. A, the guy normally doesn't sell his objects and B,
you were hiding it in your bag. Okay, those things undermine your
ability to claim that you bought it. אבל דברים שדרכן להטמין נאמן,
Aval dvarim shedarkan lehatmin ne'eman, but if it's a type of a
thing that normally you would hide, you don't want people to see,
you know, maybe it's something private, maybe it's something that's embarrassing,
the homeowner might be embarrassed, you might be embarrassed that you had
to buy
it, so in that type of a case, the fact that you're
hiding it in your bag
is not evidence that you stole it.
ושאין דרכן להטמין נמי לא אמרן, Ushe'ein darkan lehatmin nami lo amran,
and even in the case where you have to make a whole
decision tree here to follow this whole thing, things that are not
normally hidden which in that case and that's why it's so now
there are two things that are giving evidence that are creating evidence
that you did not buy it. The guy doesn't normally sell his
stuff and normally there would not be a reason for you to
be hiding it in your bag. And even that אלא איניש דלא
צניעא, ela inish delo tzniei, but only if you are not a
modest type of a person. אבל איניש דצניעא, Aval inish detzniei, if
you're a modest person, you don't like going carrying around things, you
put things in your bag, you don't go carrying big salad bowls
around in the street, it doesn't look nice, it doesn't look
modest, you're a private person, you put stuff away. אבל איניש דצניעא
היינו אורחיה, Aval inish detzniei haynu orchei, that would be normal. Okay,
so you need a really a couple of things to undermine your
claim that you bought it. Number one, the guy normally doesn't sell
his things. Number two, there's no good reason for you to be
hiding it. And there's no good reason means you both it's not
the type of thing
that would normally be hidden because maybe it's an embarrassing type of
a thing or something like that and number two you're not a
private guy that basically
puts everything away and does not like to
expose things like out there in the street. Okay, so you need
both of those. He doesn't normally sell it and there's no good
explanation why you hid it. ולא אמרן אלא זה אומר שאולין וזה
אומר לקוחין. Velo amran ela zeh omer she'ulin vezeh omer lekuchin.
And even in that case where you're not believed, it's only if
you're debating that the owner says I lent them to you and
you said I bought them, then you're not believed because then people
don't normally sell their items etc. אבל בגנובין לאו כל כמיניה, Aval
bignuvin lav kol kimeinei, but if the owner says you stole them
and you say you bought them, we would more believe you that
you bought them even though there's all this contrary evidence, people don't
normally sell stuff,
why are you hiding it etc., but we would more be prepared
to believe you bought them because אחזוקי איניש בגנבי לא מחזקינן, achzukei
inish b'ganvei lo machzikinan, we don't want to assume that people are
thieves. Okay, so in the
case we're more willing to believe it was an unlikely case of
purchase than to think that you're a גנב. ganav. So in the
case of our משנה where there's a נשבע ונוטל, if the guy
would actually say yes I did take it but I bought it,
then we would believe him. Okay, so the only thing is if
you're not making the claim of לקוחין lekuchin that's where we get
to the case of our משנה. ולא אמרן אלא
בדברים העשויין להשאיל ולהשכיר. Velo amran ela bidvarim ha'asuyin lehash'il ul'haskir. But
this case
that it's a debate, right, about the owner says I lent them
to you and you say I purchased them and we basically said
we're going to believe the owner, if he said you stole them
we wouldn't think you're a גנב, ganav, but if he says I
lent them
to you we're going to believe the owner, so that thing that
we are prepared to believe the owner is אלא בדברים העשויין להשאיל
ולהשכיר, ela bidvarim ha'asuyin lehash'il ul'haskir, the types of things that normally
would be either lent out or rented out. אבל דברים שאין עשויין
להשאיל ולהשכיר, Aval dvarim she'ein asuyin lehash'il ul'haskir, things that are normally
not lent out or rented out,
נאמן, ne'eman, okay, then actually you would be believed to say that
they're purchased. So basically we start from this big statement you're not
believed, you walk into the house and you walk out you're not
believed to say that they're purchased, and now we learn that the
only time you're not believed is in a very narrow set of
circumstances. It's only in a case where the guy normally doesn't sell
his stuff, where you hid it and you have no good explanation
why you would hide it, if you really had purchased it, and
he's claiming
that you had borrowed it and or he rented it to you,
and it's a type of a thing
that wait a minute did I get this mixed up let me
start that again.
So we start by a statement which is when you come and
when you come out you're not believed to say you purchased it
we're going to believe the owner.
So that was a general statement that we're going to believe the
owner, you're not believed to say it was purchased. But now we
understand, now we're seeing that you're only believed, you're going to believe
the owner in a, only if a lot of a lot of
criteria are satisfied. Only if the owner doesn't normally sell his stuff,
you have no explanation
why you're hiding them, it is not the types of things that
are normally normally rented or lent out. Only in all those combinations,
you know, will we believe the owner. And fine. אבל דברים שעשויין
להשאיל ולהשכיר, Aval devarim she'asuyin le'hashil u'lehaskir, but things that are not
normally lent out, so נאמן, ne'eman, then in that case, you know,
we will believe you to say that they are purchased. So
דשלח רב הונא בר אבין deshlach Rav Huna bar Avin sent the
message, דברים העשויים להשאיל ולהשכיר, devarim ha'asuyim le'hashil u'lehaskir, and you say
that they are purchased, ואמר לקוחין הן בידי, ve'amar lekuchin hen beyadi,
and you say that they're purchased, אינו נאמן, eino ne'eman, you're not
believed. כי הא דרבא, ki ha deRava, like the case of Rava,
אפיק זוגא דסרסא afik zuga desarsa וספרא דאגדתא vesafra de'agadata מיתמי miyatmi
דברים העשויים להשאיל ולהשכיר, devarim ha'asuyim le'hashil u'lehaskir,
that he went ahead and he sort of extracted, took out, you
know, like a scissors, you know, used for like in like clothing
cases, and a book of אגדתא Agadata
from orphans and somebody claimed that they were his and that he
had lent them to the father of these orphans, and I guess
it was known that it had been his, and now they're in
the possession of the orphans, and he said he had lent them
to the father of the orphans, and רבא Rava believed the guy
and handed it back to him. So what does that show you?
It shows you that the father would not have been believed to
say that they were purchased, because if the father would have been
believed to say they were purchased, then רבא Rava would have made
that claim on behalf of the orphans. So you see that when
it's something that is normally lent out and the owner goes ahead
and says that they were lent out, that you believe the owner,
the original person that we knew to be the original owner. Now,
I should make a point that these last comments seem to be
that that's all you need. All you need is דברים העשויים להשאיל
ולהשכיר devarim ha'asuyim le'hashil u'lehaskir in order to believe the original owner.
You know, whereas before when we read the גמרא, Gemara it sounded
like you needed multiple factors in order to retrieve it. It had
to be things that are normally lent out plus the בעל הבית
not doesn't normally sell his vessels plus the guy was hiding it
under his garment and didn't have a good excuse, etc., etc., etc.
So תוספות Tosafot has a different read of the earlier גמרא Gemara
based on this גמרא, Gemara and he basically says if it is
a type of a thing that is normally lent out, you don't
need any of the other factors. Before you needed the other factors
because it was a type of thing that was not normally lent
out. So according to תוספות, Tosafot, there are two ways that you
believe the owner to say that it's his. Number one, if it's
a type of thing that's normally lent out or rented and you
knew it was the owner's and now somebody else has it, the
owner is believed to say that it was lent out or rented,
it does not belong to the other person, which is again a
really big חידוש chiddush undermining the general principle or against the general
principle of חזקה מה שתחת יד אדם הרי הוא שלו chazakah mah
she'tachat yad adam harei hu shelo does not apply to things that
are normally lent out or rented out. Plus even something that is
not normally lent or rented, he's believed when you have all these
other factors: it was hidden under the garment and there's not a
good reason why it was hidden, etc., etc. Okay? So that and
that reads much better in this גמרא. Gemara. The things that are
דרכן להשאיל ולהשכיר darkan le'hashil u'lehaskir fundamentally the חזקה chazakah that תחת
יד אדם הרי הוא שלו tachat yad adam harei hu shelo does
not work. So now the גמרא says like this. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, says רבא, Rava, אפילו שומר נשבע, afilu shomer nishba, אפילו אשתו
של שומר נשבעת. afilu ishto she'shomer nishbat.
So now
we
are going back to the basic שבועה that somebody comes into the
house, takes something, and the homeowner says you took from me and
he denies it, and then the person will swear what was taken
and he would be believed. So let's say the homeowner wasn't around,
but let's say somebody else was there. Let's say the guard was
there. אפילו שומר afilu shomer doesn't mean somebody who's watching an object,
you know, somebody who's a guard of the house, or אפילו אשתו
של שומר נשבעת, afilu ishto she'shomer nishbat, even the, you know, the
shomer's wife, right? Anybody who would be around the house who might
have seen it is believed to take the שבועה on you know
in order to retrieve the vessel. Okay. בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav
Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa asks, שכיר ולקיט מאי? sachir ve'lakit mai?
תיקו. teiku. Let's say it's not somebody that normally is responsible for
watching the stuff, but somebody normally around the house, you know, so
it's like you know your hired hand. Would he be believed to
take the oath to help the בעל הבית get it back? We
don't know. אמר ליה רב יימר לרב אשי, Amlei Rav Yeimar le'Rav
Ashi, said רב יימר Rav Yeimar to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, טען
בכיסא דכספא מאי? ta'an be'kasa de'chaspa mai? Let's say that the person
says you stole a silver goblet from me, right? Worth a lot
of money. You know, I mean, if once you give the guy
the license to make a שבועה and to collect and you have
no idea what was taken, could he make an outrageous claim? Okay,
so מאי, mai, what, what's the הלכה? halacha? חזינא, Chazina, we assess
it. אי אינש אמיד הוא, Ee inish amid hu, is if he's
a rich person, או אינש דמהימן הוא o inish d'meheman hu דמפקיד
אינש גביה d'mafkid inish gabei or he is a trustworthy person that
even though he's not personally rich, other people might entrust with him
something like this, a silver goblet, then משתבע ושקיל. mishtava v'shakil. We
allow him to take the oath. ואי לא לא, v'ee lo lo,
but if there's no reason why he would have a silver goblet
in his home, we're not going to allow him to take an
oath. Okay so putting some parameters on this תקנה דרבנן. takana d'rabanan.
Okay, I want to just before we wrap up this just read
one thing in the רש"י Rashi that the גמרא said that a
book of אגדתא Agadata was something that is normally lent out. If
you look in the middle of the רש"י Rashi of מיסמי, Mi'asmi,
רש"י Rashi says like this: ודוקא ספרי דאגדתא שאין אדם עשוי ללמוד
בהם תדיר V'davka sifrei d'agadata she'ein adam asui lilmod bahem tadir
only if it's like אגדתא, Agadata, people aren't regularly learning אגדתא, Agadata,
so you would lend it out. אבל שאר ספרים אינם עשויים להשאיל
להשכיר Aval shaar sefarim einam asuyim lehashil lehashkir משום דמתקלקלים. mishum d'mitkalkelim.
Okay but other ones you don't lend out because you're afraid that
you're going to lend it out, somebody's going to a גמרא like
a real like you know something like מסכת שבועות, Masechet Shvuos, people
are going to be שטייגינג shtaiging over it and then they'll come
to damage the book. So that you would never lend out your
scroll of some like you know a like גמרא. Something that's אגדתא,
Agadata, alright, people don't read so much אגדתא Agadata so you're not
afraid, which is a pretty I think funny and ironic based on
where a lot of people's normally is attracted to learn. Okay we
will end here for today.